{
  "reference_number": "662",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "I don't believe anyone has enough information now to set those targets. With a bit of luck it could involve all parties in parliament to\n\n get an ongoing commitment to it."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": "I don't feel i (or most people are qualified to answer this at the moment). So I am opting for the weakest measure."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "International carbon units haven't worked well as there hasn't been enough safeguards on the quality of them. However provided that\n\n there are then it would make a lot of sense to make the reductions where it is easiest first. This is a global issue so should be\n handled globally. This could make quite a difference to people in the third world or heavily polluted countries were the fix may be fairly\n cheap to achieve and if supported by the sale of carbon credits it is more likely to happen."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But there should be a framework put in place at the start so that \"changed circumstances\" is defined in advance. Look at how the\n\n Electricity Authority handles low lake levels this has worked well."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "More likely to get buy in from all parties if this is included."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "For reasons above and also we are a very small contributor overall and wouldn't want to wreck our economy to maintain a principle if\nthings change to a significant extent and in a way that wasn't envisioned when the targets were set."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This consideration \"economic circumstances and, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on the economy and the\ncompetitiveness of particular sectors of the economy\" should also include wealth transfers and hardship to sectors of the economy\n\nsuch as farming. Sudden change could be very detrimental and cause considerable hardship to individuals and there would need to\nbe a significant impact on global emissions for this to be worthwhile. Change shoudl aim to be gradual to enable people to adapt."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "While we want to be world leaders we should also recognise that we are extremely small and that what we do will have little impact\n\noverall so we should not sacrifice industry and people for a lofty goal that may make little overall difference. It is also necessary that\nchange is seen to be equitable and fair otherwise it is unlikely to be durable and will be undone by future governments and\n\ngenerations."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I believe that the two items listed as desirable are in fact essential."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I couldn't find this?? Maybe I just didn't understand??"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I only had time to read the summary and some sections where the questions pointed me to it. It is a very quick off the cuff\nsubmission. I suggest that you include farming and business groups in your consultation as well as Iwi, social agencies etc. That is\n\nmake sure your consultation is far-reaching and the those groups are well represented by people who do have time to read the\ndocument throughly."
    }
  ]
}
